Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is דף י', daf
yud, and we're in the middle of the גמרא Gemara of the
עמוד, amud, and we were discussing the line in the beginning of
the משנה. Mishnah. You know, the משנה Mishnah is נדרי רשעים Nidrei
reshaim as opposed to נדרי כשרים nidrei kesherim and נדבות כשרים. nidvos
kesherim. Basically, רשעים reshaim make נדרים nedarim and כשרים kesherim make נדבות.
nidvos. And that led us onto a discussion about that in terms
of a נזיר Nazir as well. What is even the phenomenon of
a נזיר Nazir by a נדבה nidavah like? And basically what would
be a properly vowed נזיר Nazir and one that is not. Again,
it's not a technical difference like a קרבן korban could be a
נדר neder or נדבה, nidavah, but it is a question of like
motivation. And that led the גמרא Gemara to discuss the position quoting
the position of שמעון הצדיק, Shimon HaTzadik, who said he had never
met a real, or he had never eaten from the קרבן korban
of the אשם asham of a נזיר, Nazir, except for this one
particular one which, as Michael correctly said, was like a reverse narcissist
story, of somebody who truly did it לשם שמים. l'shem shamayim. And
then so that was the גמרא, Gemara, and then that was working
in with the position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says better
not to make a vow at all. And that נדרים nedarim are
basically bad. Then the גמרא Gemara essentially repeated that idea in the
position of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, right, who says like the you
know רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says טוב שלא ידור מזה ומזה שאינו
נודר כל עיקר. tov shelo yiddor mizeh mizeh she-eino noder kol ikkar.
And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said no, טוב מזה ומזה, tov mizeh
mizeh, better rather as opposed to making a vow and not fulfilling
it, the better thing is נודר ומקיים, noder u'mekayem, that you do
make a vow. But then the גמרא Gemara basically turned רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda into רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. No, no, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda just means a נדבה. nidavah. Even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda agrees
a נדר neder is not good. So anyway we basically get to
the same idea, נדרים nedarim are not good, נדבות nidavos are good.
And another idea that and then quoting רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda himself
who says the similar idea by a נזיר Nazir that that a
נזיר Nazir that a that you can have a נזיר Nazir who
makes a who's like you know who's doing it out of a
proper motivation if he's basically doing it as a way to eat
a קרבן חטאת. korban chatas. So that really sort of uses the
נדבה nidavah idea like the נדבה nidavah of giving a קרבן, korban,
this is so he can't sin so the way he gets to
eat a קרבן חטאת korban chatas like the person who heard that
it was a מצוה mitzvah for a for a person who if
he wanted to divorce his wife to give his wife a גט
get so he went out of his way to divorce his wife
so he can give her a גט. get. You know so anyway
so this person wants to go ahead and eat a קרבן חטאת,
korban chatas, bring a קרבן חטאת, korban chatas, so he he goes
ahead and makes himself a נזיר. Nazir. Anyway it's a similar type
of a נדבה nidavah way of giving that type of a of
a קרבן. korban. Either way though, it's the ideas to frame it
that like נדרים nedarim are things that we're looking down on,
נדבות nidavos are good. And what is a what how do you
apply that concept by a נזיר, Nazir, meaning it's a general like
skepticism you know because about people that are doing these types of
things. Right, that's the whole idea, that even if you're going to
fulfill it, it's not necessarily a good thing to be doing this.
So what would be a good phenomenon of that by נזירות nezirut
and then two variations of that. Yes, רבי דב. Rabbi Dov.
Could you just say a quick word about how to translate the
word רשעים? reshaim? In other words, they can't be wicked.
Yeah, I mean the ר"ן Ran says רשעים בדבר זה, reshaim badavar
zeh, you know, I don't know, inappropriate. Yeah, I know.
It's a much lighter term than a wicked human being.
That is true, that is true. But it you know it also
does reflect even though obviously רשעים reshaim does not mean its normal
full harsh statement, it's again a fascinating point in a מסכת masechet
devoted to נדרים nedarim to basically be you know having such a
disparaging statement said about people who take נדרים. nedarim. Seems a bit
contradictory. Well basically, right, and I'm going to say a little bit
more about that in a few minutes. So anyway, but yeah it's
I mean it doesn't mean רשעים reshaim in the fullest sense and
as somebody said the other day like I think David said like
who would want to say I'm going to vow like רשעים reshaim
do? You know, the whole thing is a pretty is pretty funny.
But again it is worth noting that concern about making נדרים. nedarim.
Is it because a concern that people will violate it so even
if you do fulfill it you might come to violate it or
in itself it's somewhat of a questionable religious phenomenon the idea that
you have to go ahead and make your own religious realities and
it's not enough the fact that the exactly that it's not enough
to sort of you know and that it's sort of a self-imposed
you know religious experience as opposed to doing what God has commanded.
And you know so there's a lot of issues that are at
stake here. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara basically discussed that issue by
a נזיר. Nazir. What would be a good one would be a
נזיר Nazir who's doing it to eat a קרבן korban and then
we got the position of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So let's just
pick up with רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon now. The גמרא Gemara says
about twelve lines down, I don't know, one, two, three, four, five,
something like that, fifteen lines down: רבי שמעון אומר לא נדבו בנזיר.
Rabbi Shimon omer lo nadvu b'nazir. No, people you know who would
not make a vow for a נזיר, Nazir, meaning people who wanted
to give קרבנות, korbanos, they would not become a נזיר. Nazir. אלא
הרוצה להביא עולה מתנדב ומביא שלמים מתנדב ומביא תודה וארבעה מיני לחמה
מתנדב ומביא. Ella harotzeh l'havi olah mitnaddev u'mevi, shelomim mitnaddev u'mevi, todah
v'arba'ah minei lachma mitnaddev u'mevi.
So if you wanted to bring other קרבנות korbanot that was fine.
אבל בנזירות לא התנדבו. Aval b'nezirut lo hitnadvu.
Even people that wanted to bring קרבנות korbanot and wanted to do
it totally לשם שמים. l'shem shamayim. would not accept upon themselves to
be a נזיר nazir כדי שלא יקראו חוטאים kedei shelo yikaru chotim
so they should not be called sinners שנאמר וכפר עליו מאשר חטא
על הנפש shene'emar vechiper alav measher chata al hanefesh
for what that they sinned against the soul which is understood here
not just that they became טמא tamei by a נזיר טמא nazir
tamei but they actually did injury to themselves by accepting נזירות. nezirus.
And now we're going to say אמר אביי amar Abaye so Abaye's
going to collect this sort of group these opinions שמעון הצדיק ורבי
שמעון ורבי אלעזר הקפר כולן שיטה אחת הן. Shimon Hatzadik veRabbi Shimon
veRabbi Elazar Hakapar kulan shita achas hen. All these three said one
thing or are of the same general opinion. So Abaye generally often
does this, collects different opinions of the תנאים tannaim and shows how
they are roughly in the same category. They don't literally say the
same thing. Sometimes the language again לשון נדרים משונה lashon nedarim meshuna
other places it says like כולן אמרו דבר אחד kulan amru davar
echad they all said one thing. Here it says כולן שיטה אחת
הן kulan shita achas hen but it might have something to do
with the specific language of נדרים nedarim but it means they're all
somewhat in the same category, not exactly the same. Okay, so שמעון
הצדיק Shimon Hatzadik what's the
שיטה אחת? shita achas? דנזיר חוטא הוי denazir chotei havei that
a נזיר nazir is a sinner. שמעון הצדיק ורבי שמעון הא דאמרן
Shimon Hatzadik veRabbi Shimon ha de'amran Shimon Hatzadik and Rabbi Shimon we
said. Although again the ראשונים rishonim point out that it's not exactly
the same because Shimon Hatzadik specifically emphasized the נזיר טמא nazir tamei
and that since he was a טמא tamei when he would become
טמא tamei he would regret the fact that he had become a
נזיר nazir to the begin with and that so it was particularly
the נזיר טמא nazir tamei that he said was very questionable how
deep the conviction was whereas Rabbi Shimon as we just said had
nothing to do with becoming טמא. tamei. It had to do with,
you know, נקרא חוטא nikra chotei although again the פסוק pasuk of
נקרא חוטא nikra chotei is in a case of טומאה tumah but
he's not emphasizing that it's that the problem is with a נזיר
טמא. nazir tamei. Okay
and שמעון ורבי שמעון הא דאמרן ורבי אלעזר הקפר ברבי Shimon veRabbi
Shimon ha de'amran veRabbi Elazar Hakapar beRabbi and Rabbi Elazar Hakapar beRabbi
as taught in a ברייתא. braisa. רבי אלעזר הקפר ברבי אומר וכפר
עליו מאשר חטא על הנפש Rabbi Elazar Hakapar beRabbi omer vechiper alav
measher chata al hanefesh atone from that he sinned against the soul.
וכי באיזו נפש חטא? vechi be'eizo nefesh chata? Against what soul did
this person sin? Now the simple sense of the פסוק pasuk is
he became
טמא tamei because כל טמא לנפש kol tamei lanefesh the word לנפש
lanefesh means to a person but specifically also here to a dead
person but here it's reading it could have just said מאשר חטא.
measher chata. על הנפש al hanefesh means that there was some personal
injury that was done.
אלא שציער עצמו מן היין. ella shetzier atzmo min hayayin. He denied
himself wine. והלא דברים קל וחומר vehala devarim kal vachomer and we
can make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. מה זה שלא ציער עצמו
אלא מן היין נקרא חוטא. ma ze shelo tzier atzmo ella min
hayayin nikra chotei. Somebody who only denied himself wine is called a
sinner. המצער עצמו מכל דבר על אחת כמה וכמה. hametzayer atzmo mikol
davar al achas kama vechama. How much more so someone who denies
himself from all things. מכאן כל היושב בתענית נקרא חוטא. mikan kol
hayoshev betaanis nikra chotei. Anybody who is in a who accepts upon
himself a תענית taanis is called a sinner. Again it opposes opinion
to say כל היושב בתענית נקרא קדוש. kol hayoshev betaanis nikra kadosh.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says והאי קרא בנזיר טמא כתיב.
vehai kra benazir tamei kesiv. Wait a minute that פסוק pasuk is
not just about a standard נזיר nazir is a חוטא chotei that
פסוק pasuk is specifically about a נזיר טמא. nazir tamei. So the
גמרא Gemara says no משום דשנה בחטא. mishum deshana becheit. It's because
he repeated the sin. What does it mean he repeated the sin?
So either because he became טמא tamei the period extended itself and
that therefore is particularly problematic or because both because he the sin
of denying himself the wine and then adding upon it piling upon
it the sin of becoming טמא.
tamei. Wasn't necessarily his fault though.
All right so it might have to do with a lack of,
you know, being careful and so on. It's true it could happen
without against his fault but it's understood that you know that these
situations are worse.
Funny because the תורה Torah says ויכפר עליו מחטא פתאום. vayechaper alav
mecheit pisom. It sounds like... I understand I understand I understand.
Anyway so I want to say a few things about this mostly
sort of repeating things said yesterday but I want to make first
of all one point which is important to make. So what is
the idea where why is the source that it's not a good
thing? Like שמעון הצדיק Shimon Hatzadik basically seemed to emphasize because the
motivation isn't pure. Who knows why you're doing it, right? You're doing
it because I don't know you're just angry at yourself so maybe
there's a religious component to it but maybe it's not always the
healthiest motivation or, you know, if we wanted to push that even
further point I made the other day, you know being a נזיר
nazir very much marks you societally as separate from society as somebody
who's trying to be holier, you know, and so on and there
could be a lot of issues about יוהרא yuhra and doing it,
you know, even if you're not conscious you're doing it for that
reason, you know, you're doing it in order so that you could
be one of the פרום frum one of the special ones and
so on. So there's a lot of possible questions about how pure
somebody's motivation is when they adopt all of these stringent and behavior
and particularly behaviors that mark them as separate. So that seems to
have been the focus of שמעון הצדיק. Shimon Hatzadik. The
and that's why his point is is that when the person becomes
טמא, tamei, you know, it's not a deep religious conviction. It's not
coming from like a good place and therefore is he really in
it, you know, for the long run. So that was like שמעון
הצדיק's. Shimon Hatzadik These last two emphasize that you know he's called
a sinner does not seem to be the question of the motivation,
right. It seems to be it's something that is intrinsically problematic about
the phenomenon.
And you know, you could explain that again in sort of and
here it seems to emphasize like it said here: תזיר עצמו מן
היין tazir atzmo min hayayin that as we sort of said, you
know, in any religion, you know, Judaism is
cert—there's always this—there's—you will always find like ascetic trends because, you know,
because there's this idea that, you know, idea of like, you know,
religion is some—something sort of spiritual, something beyond the physical, so there's
therefore at war with the body. Does it lead to this, you
know, mind-body dualism? And therefore there's an ideal to deny the body
and so on. You certainly find that a lot in Christianity, which
as we pointed out is a little ironic since their idea of
God is an embodied God, but okay. But in Judaism, you know,
the body is a—you know, we don't find that nearly as much,
you know. On Shabbat you're supposed to have עונג שבת, oneg Shabbat,
you know.
There were like, I don't know, the—there were sects in the Second
Temple period that on Shabbat you're forbidden to have sex, you know,
it's about a sort of spiritual—I just said you're supposed to have
sex. So, you know, obviously Judaism is a much more embodied religion,
but it's not surprising that there will be those that want to
free themselves from all the desires of the body to, you know,
and that's asceticism type of a strand, and that can explain two
opinions in the Rabbis: those that say היושב בתענית נקרא חוטא hayoshev
b'taanit nikra chotei and היושב בתענית נקרא קדוש, hayoshev b'taanit nikra kadosh,
you know, and the הרמבם Rambam says that the inclination towards the,
you know, חסידי אשכנז Chasidei Ashkenaz and the asceticism in the Middle
Ages in Ashkenazi Jewry was influenced by the Christians, and he was
very much against it and said it was an anti-Jewish idea. Of
course, really you do have both strands, and you see actually that
sort of, you know, being debated here. So that definitely seems to
be more the issues here at the end. Again, why דווקא davka
the idea of somebody who becomes טמא tamei is that because like,
you know, again, because it's like it is maybe is somewhat ambiguous
or a type of a religious value—maybe there can be under some
circumstances, you know, benefit to it. But again, the question is, but
when schleps on to doing it, to persevere in it—like we have
one day a year that's יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Maybe it's worth
one day a year to try to have that, but not to
stretch it on beyond what's appropriate. So either if it stretches on
or if the person allowed themselves to become, you know, טמא, tamei,
so maybe it's—this is not the person for whom this is the
right type of behavior. So, you know, again, meaning it's not all
black and white, even in these positions of נקרא חוטא, nikra chotei,
it's within the context of somebody who—who became טמא, tamei, so there
may be are some more limited circumstances where it would be appropriate.
The last thing that I do want to say before we then
move on to the next topic is that somebody once pointed this
out to me and I think it is so correct: that this
גמרא, Gemara, and maybe not just this גמרא, Gemara,
leads us to think about being a נזיר nazir as an issue
of asceticism, of self-denial.
But actually, you know, the only thing that the תורה Torah says
that a נזיר nazir can't do is drink wine, right? Drinks wine.
Well, well, okay, you mean like whiskey?
But besides which, the issue of drinking wine and getting drunk is
not an issue of pleasure primarily, right? It's an issue of clouding
your thinking, right? About becoming inebriated, so, you know, is an issue
about losing, you know, your full, you know, mental faculties. So, you
know, a person can totally indulge and, you know, and go to
like a smorgasbord every single night, you know, and, you know, totally,
you know, and a נזיר nazir can have sex, right? So food
and sex and all the other types of sensual pleasures are available,
it's just not wine. So it is an interesting question that we
sort of think of this in terms of—in terms of
asceticism where actually, you know, it might more be like, you know—it
still is about trying to achieve a higher spiritual plane and maybe
also it's interesting for some who want to achieve a higher spiritual
plane they do it by getting drunk, you know, or by getting
high, you know? I mean, you know, Indians they—what I mean, excuse
me, Native Americans they smoke what is it? Peyote or
something? חסידים Chasidim have a good לחיים. l'chayim. What is it? Buddhists,
what is it that they have? There was a certain
drug, an herb, or I don't know what I'm talking about. Anyway,
so, okay, so that's interesting, right? But it still could be that
like, you know, the hair gets you out—keeps you sort of separate
from society, not becoming טמא tamei to dead people also sort of
somewhat separates you from society, but you don't want to—but you want
to keep your head clear, right? As opposed to clouding, you know,
your thoughts and your judgment. So that's interesting, but it is worth
noting that it's not פשוט pashut at all that this is really
about asceticism. Okay, go for it.
I just want to know—you said this yesterday too I think. Am
I misreading the פסוקים? pesukim? When the נזיר nazir becomes בפתע פתאום
טמא, b'feta pitom tamei, doesn't that end the נזירות nezirot and we've
been talking about extending it?
No, it extends it. You still—you lose your טהרה taharah days, you
have to bring קרבנות, korbanot, הימים הראשונים יפלו, hayomim harishonim yiplu, right?
And then you resume and then you have to start it all
over again.
We just had that last week's פרשה. parsha.
I'm looking at last week's פרשה. parsha. Is it the פסוק pasuk
that says you start it all over again?
הימים הראשונים יפלו כי טמא נזרו. Hayamim harishonim yiplu ki tamei nizro.
Yeah. והזיר להשם. Vahizir la'Hashem.
וביום השמיני יביא שתי
תורים
Uvayom hashemini yavi
shtei
torim or whatever it says there.
Right. אל הכהן אל פתח אהל מועד el hacohen el petach ohel
moed ועשה הכהן אחד לחטאת vahasa hacohen echad lchatat ba ba ba
ba ba. Yeah. Gimme yeah.
Maybe I'm missing the פסוק. pasuk. I mean, I see—I'm sorry. I
mean, no no no, when it says הימים הראשונים יפלו, hayamim harishonim
yiplu, it means that you're
doing it
all
over again. Yeah. והזיר להשם
את
ימי נזרו.
Vahizir la'Hashem et yemei
nizro
What do you think והזיר להשם Vahizir la'Hashem את ימי נזרו et
yemei nizro. means? רש"י: Rashi: שיחזור וימנה נזירותו כבתחילה. sheyachzor v'yimneh nezi
ruto kevatchila. והימים הראשונים יפלו—לא יעלו מן המנין. So
that's—I mean
I don't know if there's another way to explain the verse, but
I think it's פשט. pshat. Okay. Chaim, you had a comment? Which
one?
Yeah, this idea of wine.
Through תנ"ך, Tanach, it's—the impression I get is that wine is a
symbol of תענוגי עולם הזה. taanugei olam hazeh. יין ישמח לבב אנוש.
Yayin yesamach levav enosh.
Well, יין ישמח yayin yesamach is not the same as תענוגים. taanugim.
I mean יין yayin leads people astray. יין yayin leads people to
sin. That's what you get, right? That somebody—that people are נמשכים אחרי
היין. nimshachim acharei hayayin. So I guess the question is, is it
נמשכים אחרי היין nimshachim acharei hayayin into—into sort of, you know, sensual
indulgence or נמשכים אחרי היין nimshachim acharei hayayin into, you know, if
you start getting drunk it pulls you because of—you know, I don't
think it's just about—the point is it's not just about sensual indulgence.
It gets you drunk and therefore it leads you astray because—because you're
inebriated, because you become an alcoholic and, you know, you—you constantly want
to get drunk again and again. So is it—you know, so it—it
makes you want to continue to drink. So it's not exactly the
sense of like
sensual indulgence. It's the particular power of the—of the alco—of the wine,
right?
Yeah, but and besides, by נזיר, Nazir, what is this idea of
the raisins you can't eat?
Alright, so that's just an extension. That's a safeguard, right. But the
point is is that it's not just about asceticism is not the
right label here. It's not just about sensual physical indulgence.
Which it partly is.
There are elements about that—I don't know—I'm saying just it's not all
that's what's going on here. I think it is important to acknowledge
that it's specifically about wine. Okay, last comment.
Doesn't—I mean just looking at a very, very פשט pshat level, I
mean do you think that perhaps the impetus to call נזיר חוטא
Nazir chotei is just the order that it's listed in?
Yeah, because he became טמא. tamei.
No, no, no. Because, you know, first you have גזל
הגר.
gezel
hager.
Alright, I don't want to do a whole דרשה drasha on all
of those—נדרים. nedarim. Fine. Moving on then—Right. Moving on. האומר. Haomer. Now,
so that's—okay. So that was about wrapping up the whole נזיר Nazir
discussion. Very interesting because we just read it last week's פרשה. parsha.
Now, back to—now we get finally to the idea of כונמות konamot
by נזירות. nezirut. Okay, until now we've been discussing יד yad somewhat.
Anyway, but now the משנה Mishnah turns to the issue of כונם.
konam. So let's take a look. האומר, Haomer, somebody says כונם כונח
כונס, konam, konach, konas, הרי אלו כינויים לקרבן. harei elu kinuyim l'korban.
So instead of the word קרבן, korban, you have the כ kaf
and the נ nun at the end, you have כונם konam or
כונח, konach, right? I don't know—the נ nun I guess also from
the קרבן, korban, כונח, konach, okay, or כונס. konas. Anyway, that's a
substitute for the word קרבן, korban, which is seen as like a
prime word to use by נדר. neder. הרי זה עלי קרבן. Harei
zeh alai korban. So you basically say כונם זה עלי konam zeh
alai or something like that. חרק חרך חרף, Cherek, cherech, cheref, הרי
אלו כינויים לחרם, harei elu kinuyim l'cherem, right, just switches the last
letter. So הרי זה עלי חרם. harei zeh alai cherem. נזיק נזיח
פזיח, Nazik, naziach, paziach, הרי אלו כינויים לנזירות. harei elu kinuyim l'nezirut.
So you have the נזי nazi in the beginning. פזיח Paziach is
I guess the interesting because it just both changes the first and
the last letter. Okay, the גמרא Gemara will discuss that. שבותה שקוקה
שקוקה, Shvuta, shkuka, shkuka, if you say שבותה shvuta or שקוקה, shkuka,
that sounds like שבועה. shvua. Or here's the last one is the
most interesting: נודר במוהי, noder bemohi, somebody who vows במוהי, bemohi, הרי
אלו כינויים לשבועה. harei elu kinuyim lishvua. That's a כינוי שבועה. kinuy
shvua. Now, what
does—I will say, what does במוהי bemohi mean and why does it
say נודר? noder? So first of all, in all of the texts
of the משנה, Mishnah, the גירסא girsa is נודר במוסא. noder bemosa.
And מוסא mosa is a—just an Aramaic word for שבועה. shvua. מומתא
דא, Mumata da, this, you know, it's—I think you'll see it in
the תרגום אונקלוס Targum Onkelos a lot, okay, you know, והשביע הכהן
את האשה בשבועת האלה. v'hishpia hacohen et ha'isha bishvuat ha'ala. You probably
have that right there because you've got open to נשא. Naso. I
think it says במומסה bemumsah or something. So it's just an Aramaic
word for שבועה. shvua. What is then interesting is the word נודר
noder because once again we get to
the
idea— It's just a technical
difference between a נדר neder, *neder* and a שבועה shvuah? *shavuah*; sometimes
they're used interchangeably and that's why we have נדר neder בלשון שבועה
shvua *neder beloshon shavuah*, שבועה shvua. בלשון נדר neder. *shavuah beloshon neder*
in the sort of vernacular. It was used somewhat; sometimes you would
say נודר *noder* when you really mean to take a שבועה shvuah
*shavuah*, although it is ironic. Here we're talking about the language for
a שבועה shvuah, *shavuah* and we use the verb of
נודר *noder*. Anyway, that's if the version was במוסא be-mosa *bemosa*, בממטא
*bemomota* or something, which then would just be an Aramaic word for
שבועה shvuah *shavuah*. Our
version here במוהי ba-mohi, *bemohi* and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* seems to
say that מוהי Mohi *mohi* is a כינוי kinuy *kinoy* for משה
Moshe. *Moshe*, משה Moshe רבינו *Moshe Rabbeinu*, and it means that you
take a שבועה shvuah? *shavuah*, you say like the שבועה *shavuah* of
משה Moshe. *Moshe*. Now when did משה *Moshe* take a שבועה *shavuah*?
So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi, *Yerushalmi* quotes a פסוק *pasuk* that says ויואל
משה לשבת את האיש *vayoel Moshe lasheves es haish*. So we normally
translate that to mean that משה *Moshe* desired, consented, but הנה נא
הואלתי לדבר אל El השם ואנכי עפר ואפר *hinei na hoalti ledaber
el Hashem veanochi afar vaeifer*, right? ויואל *vayoel* means to desire to
and so on, but it seems that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* is
reading it from the word אלה *alah*, right, which is a curse,
or it could be לאלה ולשבועה *lealah ulishvuah*. So ויואל משה *vayoel
Moshe*, משה *Moshe* took an oath. So במוהי *bemohi* it reads that
you take an oath and you say like as the oath that
משה *Moshe* took, seems to be how the ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* reads
that. Alright, so let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
now. איתמר *itmar*,
it was said, כינויים kinuyim *kinuyim*, what are these כינויים kinoyim *kinuyim*?
רבי יוחנן Rav Yochanan אמר לשון אומות lashon umos, הן *Rabbi Yochanan
amar loshon umos hein*, they are some type of other language. Of
course, probably it has to be a Semitic language because it sounds
pretty similar to the original Hebrew term. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish אמר
לשון Lashon שבדדו להם חכמים ויהא נודר בהם *Reish Lakish amar loshon
shebadu lahem chachamim veyei noder bahem*, a language that the rabbis invented
to create as a substitute terms not to use the actual official
term. Okay, and I should remind you that there's a debate of
the ראשונים *rishonim* that if you use these כינויים kinoyim, *kinuyim*, is
it binding דאורייתא *deoraisa* or only דרבנן *derabbanan*? The ר"ן Ran *Ran*
strongly argues that it's דאורייתא *deoraisa* because first of all he says
all languages are convention, so who cares if the rabbis invented? Still,
you do wonder how widespread do they have to be held, like
is pig latin a real language? I mean how much of it
is like the natural language of a people before it gets into
the status of a language? But
besides that all languages are convention, okay, but at least a כינוי
kinuy? *kinoy* should be effectively like
why would a כינוי kinuy *kinoy* be worse than a type of
a יד yad. *yad*? Alright, so even if it's not technically the
official, even if this word is a little bit of a gibberish,
it's clear what you're trying to say. So anyway,
there is the position, so generally it's assumed that even if it's
לשון שבדדו חכמים *loshon shebadu chachamim*, it's invented, it still is binding
דאורייתא *deoraisa*, although there is an opinion that it's only binding דרבנן
*derabbanan*. וכן הוא אומר omer: *vechein hu omer*, and similarly it says
בחודש אשר בדא מלבו *bachodesh asher bada milibo*, okay, the month that
he invented from his heart, which is a little bit bizarre. What's
it telling us? What the word בדאו *badu* mean? I mean בדאו
*badu* wasn't in the משנה *mishnah*, you're quoting a פסוק *pasuk* to
tell me why ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* used the word בדאו *badu*,
it's a little bit funny.
But maybe this pointing to the idea that people have invented like
these religious phenomenon. Who's that by? Was that by חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu* or
somebody who basically added an extra חודש *chodesh* to the calendar I
think or whatever. Anyway,
so it is funny, but again maybe why quote that פסוק *pasuk*,
but maybe what it's pointing to, a little bit back to our
earlier discussion, is on the one hand the whole phenomenon of נדרים
nedarim. *nedarim* is people creating religious realities. That's a type of בדאו
מלבו *badu milibo*, right?
Is it a proof text for the authenticity of so to speak
creating something?
Yeah, except there the problem was that it was being criticized, not
condoned, right? It was not real, it
wouldn't have been different.
Okay, but I do think that that's what's going on, I think
that there's an interesting irony or if you want parallel here, the
whole phenomenon of נדרים nedarim *nedarim* is being בודה מלבו *bodeh milibo*.
I've now turned a piece of bread into something that's טרף *treif*
to eat, right? It's something that I basically created, so the rabbis
also going to create a language to use for this, and maybe
also to like downgrade it a little and again this idea of
אשר בדאו מלבו *asher badu milibo* might also be like somehow signaling,
it is interesting these signals that we're getting about that this is
somehow something problematic. So we're going to use a pretend language and
make it to have this pre, to make up
our own little religious phenomenon here. Okay, so וטעמא מאי תקינו רבנן
כינויים *vetaama mai tikinu rabbanan kinuyim*, so why would they have established
it? Presumably this is a question according to ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*,
why did they invent this language? But it might even be according
to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*, and even if it's לשון
אומות *loshon umos*, it's sort of understanding that if the rabbis are
putting it out there, they're somehow recommending it or something, but it's
certainly a question to ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*. דלא לימא קרבן Korban
*delo leima korban*, so you shouldn't say the official word קרבן korban,
*korban*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ולימא קרבן korban *vileima korban*,
so say the word קרבן korban *korban*. No, דילמא אמר קרבן להשם
Korban la-Hashem *dilma amar korban l'hashem*, because then the natural end of
the word קרבן korban *korban* would be this is a קרבן להשם
Korban la-Hashem, *korban l'hashem*.
ולימא קרבן להשם Korban la-Hashem, *vileima korban l'hashem*, right?
ולימא קרבן להשם Korban la-Hashem. *vileima korban l'hashem*, so say that. הרי
זה כקרבן להשם la-Hashem. *harei zeh kekorban l'hashem*, although it's a funny
thing to say about a loaf of bread, but anyway the
Yeah, because there's not a classic phrase, meaning there's not, you know,
in your mind and in our sort of our
cultural heritage, we don't have a phrase כונח konach, להשם. קרבן la-Hashem
Korban, triggers קרבן להשם Korban la-Hashem, in your mind, right, in terms
of, you know, but whereas כונח, konach yeah, whereas כונח does not.
Okay, and if you start saying קרבן להשם, Korban la-Hashem. then you'll
start just saying להשם. la-Hashem Okay,
וקא מביא שם שמים לבטלה. ve-ka mavi shem shamayim levatala. Let's take
a look. לבטלה, Levatala, דתניא, detanya, we
learned in a ברייתא, braita, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר: מנין שלא
יאמר אדם להשם עולה, להשם מנחה, להשם תודה, להשם שלמים? Minayin shelo
yomar adam la-Hashem ola, la-Hashem mincha, la-Hashem toda, la-Hashem shelamim? You shouldn't
say the word להשם la-Hashem first. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar קרבן להשם,
Korban la-Hashem, so להשם la-Hashem comes second. Okay, וקל וחומר, ve-kal vachomer,
ומה זה שלא נתכוון אלא להזכיר שם שמים על הקרבן, uma ze
shelo nitkaven ela lehazkir shem shamayim al ha-korban, you wanted to give
a קרבן, korban, we're doing something totally acceptable, אמרה תורה Amra Torah
קרבן להשם. Korban la-Hashem, You say קרבן korban, first and להשם la-Hashem
second, so you shouldn't say להשם la-Hashem. either because then you'll stop,
you won't have said קרבן Korban, at the end and it'll be
לבטלה. levatala. Or maybe even if you do say קרבן korban, at
the end, you know, you don't lead with the להשם. la-Hashem. It's
not showing that name enough reverence, right? And it's not giving it
enough context. You want to bring it in after you've given it
the proper context. Okay,
so המזכיר שם שמים, ha-mazkir shem shamayim, so אלא להזכירם ela lehazkiram
לבטלה levatala
על אחת כמה וכמה. al achat kama ve-khama. Somebody who says it
without any purpose, how much more so is that a terrible thing.
So if you say, if you say קרבן להשם, Korban la-Hashem next
time you'll say להשם קרבן, la-Hashem Korban and maybe you'll just next
time say להשם. la-Hashem And again, will that really be לבטלה? levatala?
Maybe it won't be לבטלה, levatala, but it's certainly not showing it
the proper respect. And maybe it will be לבטלה levatala if you
don't end the word with קרבן, korban. then it doesn't really have
like any meaning. Of course, it also is funny, right, because the
idea of להשם la-Hashem as a relevant idea for a נדר, neder?
like it does harken to again, the paradigm of נדר neder, is
devoting something to God. וידור יעקב נדר, Vayidor Yaakov neder, right, giving
מעשר, ma'aser, giving a קרבן, korban, etc. So the להשם la-Hashem is
relevant aspect of the prime concept of נדר. neder But when you're
making this loaf of bread forbidden on you, the להשם la-Hashem concept
is really not relevant at all and therefore, you know, maybe it's
inappropriate at all to be saying להשם la-Hashem, in the context of
standard נדרים.
Nedarim's Yes, there's a funny argument here. This is the strongest argument
for the authenticity of a יד. yad. In other words, it's a
trope. The minute you say להשם, la-Hashem you're already triggering in your
mind קרבן korban להשם. la-Hashem. Right?
The minute you
say קרבן, korban, it should work, it should be a יד. yad?
So again, I don't think that the גמרא Gemara is saying it
doesn't work. I mean, I think there's two questions here. If somebody
said כיכר זה להשם, kikar ze la-Hashem, right? Would that be a
נדר? neder I mean, maybe it would be a donation to the
בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So A, it's possible it doesn't work. It's
possible that the להשם la-Hashem only works when you're really doing a
קרבן, korban, when you're really giving something להשם. la-Hashem. It's possible that
it wouldn't work at all as a נדר, neder. right? But the
גמרא Gemara and that's point number one. Point number two is it
could be maybe even it does work, it's not proper to be
מזכיר שם שמים mazkir shem shamayim particularly by a נדר neder, where
you're not really giving it to God. So even if להשם la-Hashem
meant כיכר זה אסור עלי kikar ze assur alai like a קרבן
korban, להשם, this is not the right context to be saying שם
השם. shem Hashem. And again, it is fascinating to remember that the
גמרא Gemara just like two דפים dapim ago went to town about
מזכיר שם שמים mazkir shem shamayim right לבטלה. levatala. So there clearly
is with all this stuff about נדרים taking place, there's this anxiety
about, you know, A, they're רשעים, resha'im, you know, they're not doing
it for the whatever, it's not necessarily an appropriate phenomenon, you're saying
the wrong things, we got to switch the language, you might be
saying שם השם. shem Hashem. There's all this hesitancy around this whole
phenomenon.
But what I still don't understand is, I mean,
this is you shouldn't even do this in the context of an
actual קרבן. korban. You're bringing it to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash
and you say it and you have to מקדיש makdish it anyway.
Right? And you still have to use God's name, you still say
להשם.
Right? Introduce God's name when it's appropriate.
But it still is appropriate. Meaning, like you still have to say
להשם קרבן Korban. or just קרבן Korban להשם, whatever you're going to
do, right? So all you did is you still have to say
the same two words, you just switch the order and somehow that
makes it...
Yeah, sure, because it's not showing the proper יראה, yirah, right?
Introducing His Greatest Most Highness, the revered so-and-so, King George, right, as
opposed to King George, I'd like you to meet Michael. Right? Okay.
So what?
Because I'm just
thinking, you know, you don't just start with שם השם. shem Hashem.
Okay, number one.
And number two, you're still saying, you're just saying קרבן Korban להשם
first.
I understand, but you're recognizing that's not the first word out of
your mouth and you give it the right context. You don't just
say God's name without any context.
And does it have any bearing, I mean I know some Sephardim
when they get an עליה aliyah they say השם עמכם. Hashem imachem.
Is that a problem?
Well, you know that's interesting because that's a... so there's a whole
discussion in מסכת ברכות Masechet Berachot about השם עמכם. Hashem imachem. I
know, there's a whole discussion in מסכת ברכות Masechet Berachot about using
the way בועז Boaz would greet his workers as bringing in שם
השם shem Hashem into our discourse. But how do you do it
in a way with the proper sort of, you know, context that
it's not
לבטלה? levatala? Not just להשם to say it out fully, yeah. I
mean, not the שם המפורש, shem ha-meforash, but yeah. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: לימא כתנאי. lema kitnai.
So maybe this debate of רבי יוחנן and ריש לקיש is like
a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. בית שמאי אומרים: Beis Shammai omrim: כינויי
כינויים אסורים, kinuyei kinuyim assurim, ובית הלל אומרים: uveit Hillel omrim: כינויי
כינויים מותרים. kinuyei kinuyim muttarim. How about a כינוי kinoy. of a
כינוי? kinoy
So this is like instead of saying קונם, Konam, you say, well
the גמרא Gemara will say like you say, I don't know, קונמא
Konama or something like that. You know, something that's a derivation of
a derivation. So is that a problem or not? What does אסורים
assurim mean,
that it then becomes a נדר neder. or you can't do it?
What does it... No, no, it becomes a נדר. Neder. Okay. מאי
לאו, mai lav, מאן דאמר man de-amar כינויי כינויים אסורים, kinuyei kinuyim
assurim, that it's binding, קסבר kasavar כינויים לשון אומות הן, kinuyim lashon
umos hein, that it's another language and if it's another language, so
you can also have a corruption, you know, of that language and
it's still whatever, it's still real word, a real language. ולמאן דאמר
מותרים, u-le-man de-amar muttarim, the one that says it's permissible, קסבר kasavar
לשון שבדו להם חכמים, lashon she-badu lahem chachamim, that it's something invented.
So they only invented the first level, they didn't invent the derivation
of that language. Okay, and you know, it's only what they said
works, it's not variations and derivations of it. So the גמרא Gemara
says: לא דכולי עלמא lo de-chulei alma כינויים לשון אומות הן. kinuyim
lashon umos hein. We could say everybody says it's some other language.
Again, it's a very funny other language that sounds very similar to
the Hebrew, but okay. ובית שמאי סברי u-Veis Shammai savri בהני נמי
משתעי אומות, ba-hanei nami mishta-ei umos, and now the way the רן
Ran explains this is, yes, it's another language, but clearly this is
a corruption of the other language. That's why it's כינויי כינויים. kinuyei
kinuyim. So בית שמאי Beis Shammai holds that this corruption is still
considered legitimate, like people speak this language and it's enough to be
considered a legitimate variation. ובית הלל סברי בהני לא משתעי. u-Veis Hillel
savri ba-hanei lo mishta-ei. People don't talk, and it doesn't mean like
they don't talk at all, but the גמרא Gemara, says like the
רן Ran says, it's not מעיקר הלשון, me-ikar ha-lashon, right? Is it
a dialect, right? Or is it not even considered like a legitimate
dialect of the language? So, you know, that's great questions, right? Like
if you think about American English, what are the things we're prepared
to call a dialect and what are the things that we call
as corruptions of the language? Okay, so that would be the issue.
Okay.
That would be a good question.
Exactly. ובית הלל סברי u-Veis Hillel savri בהני לא משתעי. ba-hanei lo
mishta-ei.
ואיבעית אימא: ve-iba-is eima: בית שמאי סברי Beis
Shammai savri גזרינן כינויי כינויים משום כינויים. gazrinan kinuyei kinuyim mishum kinuyim.
Everybody might say that this is, you know, not really, does not
really work, either because it's not a real version of the language
or because כינויים are an invented language and this certainly isn't included,
but nevertheless we're going to make it as a safeguard and say
it is binding, at least rabbinically. ובית הלל סברי u-Veis Hillel savri
לא גזרינן כינויי כינויים משום כינויים. lo gazrinan kinuyei kinuyim mishum kinuyim.
We're not גוזר. gozer. Fine. Okay, but we still don't know whether
it's something invented or whether it is some type of variant language.
היכי דמי כינויי כינויים? heichi dami kinuyei kinuyim? What would be an
example of this? דנדרים: de-nedarim: תני רב יוסף, tani Rav Yosef, so
as opposed to קונם, Konam, you said מקנמנא. mekanamna. As opposed to
קונח, Konach, you said מקנחנא. mekanachna. As opposed to קונס, Konas, you
said מקנסנא. mekanasna. Okay,
so I don't know if you said מקנסנא זה עלי mekanasna zeh
alai or you said מקנסנא mekanasna sounds more like a verbal form
of it. I am making this a קונם, Konam, I am making
this a קונס Konas or something like that. Anyway, so that would
be a כינויי כינויים. kinuyei kinuyim. היכי דמי כינויי כינויים דחרם? heichi
dami kinuyei kinuyim de-cherem? What would be a חרם cherem example of
this? תני מפשע, tani Mafsha, I don't know who that is: חרקים
חרכים חרכים charkim charchim charchim as opposed to
חרך חרך חרך.
cherekh cherekh cherekh.
Fine, you pluralized it. כינויי כינויים דנזירות: kinuyei kinuyim de-nezirus: תני רב
יוסף, tani Rav Yosef, מחזקנא mechazakna as opposed to חיזק. chezek. It's
מחזקנא. mechazakna. As opposed to נזיח, naziach, it's מנזחנא. menazachna. As opposed
to פזיח, paziach, it's מפיחנא. maphichna. Fine.
איבעית להו, iba-is lehu, and they wanted to
ask: מפחזנא מאי? mi-pachazna mai? מתחזנא מאי? mi-thazana mai? מתאזנא מאי? mi-tazana
mai? I don't know how those are supposed to be given, they're
even more derivation. So presumably, I don't know, because כינויי כינויים kinuyei
kinuyim are like בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, like בית הלל Beis Hillel
is no good, these seem to be even more of a derivation
than a כינויי כינויים. kinuyei kinuyim. So what's the question according to
בית
שמאי?
Beis
Shammai?
Not understanding where to draw the line.
Yeah, I don't know anyway. Fine. All right, moving on. That's why
there's basically no רן Ran on this. Okay, so אמר ליה רבינא
לרב אשי, amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi, רבינא Ravina said to רב
אשי: Rav Ashi: קינמא מאי? kinama mai? Let's say somebody said קינמא,
kinama, which sounds a lot like קונם. Konam. So what's the story?
קונם קאמר Konam ka-amar או דילמא קינמון בוסם קאמר?
o dilma kinmon bosem
ka-amar? It's a spice. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב חייא לרב
אשי: amar lei Rav Acha berei de-Rav Chiya le-Rav Ashi: קינא מאי?
kina mai?
קינא? Kina? קינא של תרנגולים קאמר, kina shel tarnegolim ka-amar, does it
mean like a chicken rooster coop? או דילמא o dilma לשון דקונם?
lashon de-konam? Maybe קינא kina sounds like קונם. Konam.
I think קינא kina is in איכה.
Eicha. That too. תיקו. teiku. Okay, we don't know. So is that
also a כינוי kinoy or not? Or is it a כינויי כינויים?
kinuyei kinuyim? Because
it's a question because כינויי כינויים kinuyei kinuyim are not binding according
to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, so the question is maybe whether those
are כינויי כינויים kinuyei kinuyim or is it... Anyway, כינויי דשבועה היכי
דמי? Kinoyei deshvuah heichei dami? What's the כינויים of שבועה?
שבותאל, Shvuel, he is the תיבעי.
Tee-bai. Well,
it's the נדרים version of the word תיקו. teiku. Okay, שבותאל, Shvuel,
שבותיאל, Shvutiel, שקוקיאל, Shkukiel, שבותאל, Shvuel, okay, okay, so those are them.
שבותאל, Shvuel, שבותיאל, Shvutiel, שקוקא אל. Shkukael. Notice by the way the
word אל in here, so it might be like a שבועה to
God. Okay, but it's a nevertheless even though it's like a hybrid,
it's yet a further created word.
So it's, again, I think it is interesting that it could be
the word like ויפרקונם, va-yefrakonam, מכנמנא miknamna is turned it into a
verb form as opposed to הרי זה עלי כונם, Harei zeh alaikonam,
you're saying מכנמנא miknamna I'm making this a כונם. konam. But nevertheless,
it's yet a further derivation. Here what you're doing is you're adding
God's name to it, which is what you would do for a
שבועה. The גמרא Gemara says, שבותאל. Shvuel. What do you mean שבותאל?
Shvuel? שבותאל בן גרשום משמע. Shvuel ben Gershom mashma. Apparently there was
somebody by the name of שבותאל בן גרשום. Shvuel ben Gershom. I
didn't check my concordance. But anyway, says the גמרא, Gemara אלא שבותא
אל, Ella Shvuba-el, fine. Okay, now, the גמרא wants to know שבותא
אל, Shvuba-el, שבותיאל, Shvutiel, שקוקא אל. Shkukael. That's what we wanted to
know. They take out the word מהו, mahu, I'm not, that would
be כינויי כינויים. kinuy kinuyim. We take out the word מהו. mahu.
אמר שמואל. Amar Shmuel. So שמואל Shmuel says, אמר אשישתא לא אמר
כלום. Amar ashishta lo amar klum. If somebody tried to make again
some type of a verb form of this, it's not good. אשקיקה
לא אמר כלום. Ashkika lo amar klum. Okay,
כרישנא, Karishna, I don't know כרינשא, Karinsa, I don't know Harry, what
is it? The Harry Krishnas? Okay, כרינשא לא אמר כלום Karinsa lo
amar klum or כרסנתא. Kursanta. Anyway, somehow if you made it some
verb form. All right, that was wonderful. So some things are כינויים,
some things are כינויי כינויים, kinuyey kinuyim, some things we don't know
which paragraph they, which category they're in. נדר במוהי הרי אלו לכינויים.
Neder be-mohi harei elu l'kinuyim. So again we said that either means
במוסא which is just the language of שבועה in the, of the
Aramaic of the word שבועה, or the way the ירושלמי Yerushalmi understands
it, it means a, what do you call it, it means משה.
So and that presumably is how we're going to read this ברייתא.
braita. תניא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר: Tanya Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer: האומר במוהי, Ha-omer ba-mohi, if you said just במוהי, לא אמר
כלום lo amar klum because that's like saying, the way again this
is read through the lens of the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, it's like just
saying במשה. Be-Moshe. Then לא אמר כלום. lo amar klum. במומסא דאמר
מוהי, Be-mumsah de-amar mohi,
in the שבועה that משה said, הרי אלו כינויים לשבועה, harei elu
kinuyim le-shvuah, that is a כינוי. kinoy Of course then the question
is why is it a כינוי kinoy if the word מומסא mumsah
just is the Aramaic word for שבועה? I mean I guess it's
a כינוי kinoy, according to רבי יוחנן of לשון אומות, but it's
the least of any of them, it's just a translation. מוהי mohi
I guess is the כינוי kinuy. because מוהי is a כינוי kinuy
for the word משה. Now,
the ירושלמי interestingly adds, like of all these things, the ירושלמי throws
in two things which are probably the most natural. The ירושלמי says,
האומר ימין הרי זה שבועה, Ha-omer yamin harei zeh shvuah, האומר שמאל
הרי זה שבועה. Ha-omer smol harei zeh shvuah. Like I raise up
my right hand, right? נשבעתי, Nishbati, what is it, you know, נשבעתי
בימיני, nishbati bi-yemini, right? You know, you know or like the פסוקים
psukim sometimes say God says like you know הרימותי ידי אל ה',
harimoti yadi el Hashem, right? So he says, by my right hand,
ימין הרי זה שבועה, yamin harei zeh shvuah, שמאל הרי זה. smol
harei zeh. That I actually understand where that's coming from.
Why שמאל, smol, no one takes one?
I don't know. Okay, so he's a lefty. Now wait, I want
to say something. So Saul Lieberman in a, has a whole article
here in his book, Greek and Jewish Palestine called Oaths and Vows.
I'm happy to
xerox this for people if they want it, but it's not necessarily
an easy article to read because it's very terse and very technical.
Anyway, some but he basically talks a lot about all of these
phenomenon and he points out that in in the
among the gentiles in the Roman society at the time like people
would make oaths and vows like just pile them up one on
top of the other and they would make them in the name
of stupid things like they'd say in the name of the dog,
in the name of the lettuce, in the name of the whatever
and sometimes that actually was because of a they didn't want to
say the name of their gods so they used it as a
type of a כינוי, Kinnuy right? So he points out about how
a lot of these phenomenon were common amongst the non-Jews as well
and that gets to those whole issue about the rabbis sort of
trying to regulate it and trying to say okay this is silly
this doesn't mean anything you know this means something serious on the
one hand. And part of the problem is that every like if
people just said it they said it for the I mean he
has a line here they said it for the stupidest things so
nobody took them seriously right it says like this it says the
rabbis constantly and repeatedly preached it's preferable entirely to abstain from swearing.
One is considered a sinner.
True,
the rabbis themselves often swore but they were entitled and qualified to
decide whether their oaths were justified by necessity. The people on the
other hand swore in their houses, in the street, and in the
market, both in general conversations and in business matters and they had
to be checked in one way or another. The older rabbinic sources
speak of substitutes. They mention handles, hoping thereby to eliminate the pronounce-
pronunciation of the holy words and the vow formulas. But the question
arises were these artificial inventions of the rabbis for the purposes of
preventing the people from
swearing? Well, maybe, right? That's interesting, ואומות העולם *VeUmot HaOlam* I'm thinking
about also, right? Anyway, the correct answer, anyway, basically he says is
clearly the second. There is clearly this widespread usage, there was a
lot of sort of just sloppy and different types of terms and
the Rabbis tried to somehow control and regulate this, and he shows
that a lot of the examples in the מסכת *Masechet* about people
taking vows, you know, and the types of vows that they took,
actually make sense if you look in the context of what we
know about from, you know, the non-Jews there. The Gentile populace in
Greece resorted to oaths in their ordinary talks, in the streets, in
the markets, even for the purpose of cheating and out of mere
verbosity. Now you think about people nowadays, right? That they curse not
because they really want to curse, it's just like every other word
is a curse word, right? The populace of Alexandria in Egypt did
not behave any better. Philo remarks, "So it's highly impious are they,
that on any chance matter the most tremendous titles are on their
lips, and they do not blush to use name after name, one
piled upon another, thinking that the continual repetition of a string of
oaths will secure them their object." Okay.
The same can be said in Palestine. The people swore and adjured
on every occasion. They affirmed their statements, says Saul Lieberman, by an
oath in business affairs and formulas of courtesy when they invited their
friends, accepted invitations or rejected them, and in support of stories which
strain credulity. Okay, and then he goes on to discuss, you know,
about this. So some of the interesting things that he points out
here is first of all the use of the language of the
word נודר *Noder* when it really means to take a שבועה *Shevua*.
So he actually says that, I mean, he gives a lot of
examples about the words of use of the word נודר *Noder* that
the Rabbis when they want to say is even though there might
be a technical difference, it's a word that the Rabbis used to
mean to take a שבועה *Shevua*, and he actually points to an
interesting מדרש *Midrash* that says the difference to say to take a
שבועה *Shevua* in God's name or to be נודר *Noder* in God's
name, and here we don't mean our נדרים *Nedarim*, we mean to
take a שבועה *Shevua*, right? But the difference is whether you're נשבע
בחיי המלך *Nishba BeChayei HaMelech* or במלך עצמו *BeMelech Atzmo*. And so
it's interesting like what exactly that difference means, but that anyway he
does point out a, so he goes on a little bit about
that. And then he sort of speaks about,
I mean like again, like just a very different, like there was
a type of language that the Rabbis used, a type of language
that the common people used.
I'll just read you one other thing here he says.
But the Jewish masses also invented. Here.
We can now summarize the conflict between the opinion of the majority
of the learned Rabbis and the popular belief of the masses. The
people, in their fear of the real oath, began to swear not
only by holy objects, just like the next משנה *Mishna*, like Jerusalem,
the Temple, the altar, the קורבן *Korban*, that's actually the next משנה
*Mishna* that's coming up, but by all kinds of matter, beginning with
the heaven and the earth, the sun, and ending with absurd oaths
like by the fishnet and by the life of the fig picker.
No sooner did absurd expressions become a fixed oath term that the
people tended to use it as a substitute, progressing from the stupid
to the ridiculous. Okay.
Anyway, some Rabbis were ready to make concessions to the excessive popular
zeal, but the majority, in their hatred of foolish saints who wear
out the world, abide by the strict opinion that all these popular
oaths are null and void. But the Jewish masses also invented all
kinds of substitutes for valid and binding terms, as קורבן *Korban*, נדר
*Neder*, חרם *Cherem*, נדר שבועה *Neder Shevua*, etc., in order to avoid
for one reason or another the utterance of these terms. In this
case, the Rabbis had to confirm a great part of the substitute.
Here they had to accept the rule that we go by the
language of the people. Okay, and then he says לשון שביררו להם
ראשונים *Lashon SheBireru Lahem Rishonim* or etc., you know, and so on
about this whole idea of, you know, לשון שבדו *Lashon SheBadu*. So
the interesting thing about his claim is that it's less לשון שבדו
חכמים להיות נודרים בהן *Lashon SheBadu Chachamim Lihyot Noderim Bahen* and more
it's that the masses already, because of their fear and because of
their desire for substitutes, were already using all of these
substitutes
and perversions and even to the point of ridiculous because it was
so much even out of the realm and the Rabbis had to
like pull it in and say, "Wait, only these are close enough
to really be binding. A lot of what you guys are doing
is not even binding." And maybe that's somewhat of the כינויי כינויים
*Kinnuyei Kinnuyim* type of discussion around those lines, yes.
The discussion of substitutes, of substitutes in the גמרא *Gemara* are words
that are linguistically related, right? But the גמרא *Gemara* is full of
like Greek and Latin words, so they don't
discuss those as Greek words.
Right, so some of that is discussed in this. I'll make, I'll
copy off the article if you want to read in more detail.
Yeah, in every oath you said you take a שבועה *Shevua* like
משה *Moshe*. I mean, is that, does it really say משה *Moshe*?
But let's say you took a שבועה *Shevua* and then I say
I make a שבועה *Shevua* like Rabbi Linszer did.
Is it the
same thing or?
Yeah, I mean, presumably the whole חידוש *Chidush* is that the word
במוהי *Bamohi* here is, you know, you have to tell me that
that
means במשה *BeMoshe* or maybe it
just
means...
would include another word besides the name of God.
Right, so that so I mean, yeah. I don't, oh, I don't
know. That that I don't know.
It's an interesting question whether some people want to apply that to
a כינוי of God and שם שמים לבטלה, shem shamayim l'vatalah, that's
not my normal sense. But what I thought you were going was
also the point that, yes, part of this whole idea about, you
know again, it's interesting because if through the way that Lieberman presents
it, it's not like the rabbis are coming in and imposing this
concern of שם שמים לבטלה, shem shamayim l'vatalah, it's that the people
themselves are on the one hand being way too prolifigate with their
vows. They're doing it all the time. On the other hand, because
they're doing it all the time, they're doing it, they're not using
the heavy words, they're using these lighter words, right? So it's sort
of like you lose both ways, you know? I mean, it's a,
it's not a binding vow, I mean, anyway, so it's interesting that
the rabbis sort of trying to approach this phenomenon. You've got the
almost the fear of שם שמים לבטלה shem shamayim l'vatalah going out
there, but then it becomes a prolific use of the vows. So
it's trying to like sort of like readjust that, you know?
But yeah, this is really deep in every, like instead of saying
'By God', so in English you say 'By
gosh' or 'By golly'.
In other words, it's really deep. Yeah, gosh darn it, right, using
the כינוי.
Right, exactly, exactly. Right, so okay, so right, so you have this
whole thing about trying to, you know, identify only what terms used,
maintain that sense, it's like maintaining that sense of the fear of
שם שמים לבטלה, shem shamayim l'vatalah, these isn't just only שם שמים,
shem shamayim, it's even just the powerful vow words, right, maintain that
weight of that, but then but also say, but okay, but we
also have to limit therefore what is going to be a legitimate
substitute of that and what's just going to be stupid and not
meaningful. Okay, so now the גמרא says, האומר לחולין שאוכל לך. ha'omer
l'chulin she'ochel lach.
Okay, so now in Palestinian Aramaic, which seems to be what this
is, לחולין, l'chulin, the 'la' is, and this often is what trips
people up when they read ירושלמי, is that they don't understand this,
means 'la' as a prefix means 'not'. So 'not chulin'. I will,
so you know, something is un-chulin. Right, so if something is un-chulin,
it means it's קודש. kodesh. Okay, so not חולין chulin that I
will eat of this that I will eat of it, which means
so like קונם שאוכל לך. konam she'ochel lach. That thing of yours
that I will eat is הקדש, hekdesh, is קונם, konam, is אסור.
asur. So לחולין l'chulin becomes a word of
הקדש. hekdesh. Okay, לא כשר lo kasher or
לכשר, la'kasher, לא דכי, lo dachi, okay, or לא טהור. lo tahor.
And then it just says the word טהור. tahor. So the ר"ן
Ran says that presumably the right גרסא girsa based on the רמב"ם
Rambam here is לא טהור la'tahor as well, לא טהור. lo tahor.
So although טהור tahor could be as opposed to טמא tamei and
כשר kasher could be as opposed to like not kosher like חזיר
chazir and that's not a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur, right, it only
needs to be a קרבן, Korban but you could understand that no,
that it also does refer to something that isn't kosher, it would
be something that would be like פיגול pigul or נותר notar or
something like that that could be an idea of a דבר הנדור
davar hanadur that it's or an עולה olah that you're not allowed
to eat. And similarly טמא, tamei, you know, could mean טומאה tumah
like a קרבן Korban, becomes טמא, tamei, although there's a lot of
other forms of טומאה. tumah. So the ר"ן Ran says it's not
clearly means דבר הנדור davar hanadur because again, if I said this
is like חזיר, chazir, לא אמר כלום. lo amar klum. And that
maybe is our more instinctive reaction of something not kosher, I don't
think about a קרבן, Korban. I think about חזיר. chazir. Nevertheless, this
principle of like, you know, is like
is like that you go לחומרא, l'chumra, the line in the רב"ן
Raban in the ר"ן Ran? is, where's the ר"ן? Ran
If you look at the last line of the ר"ן here on
our דף, daf,
he says like וכי תימא אלא אסור משום איסור קאמר ולא משום
נדר הוה ליה כמתפיס בדבר האסור ולא מיתסר אפילו הכי כיון דאיכא
למימר הכי ואיכא למימר הכי אזלינן לחומרא דקיימא לן סתם נדרים להחמיר.
v'chi teima ela asur mishum issur ka'amar v'lo mishum neder hava lei
k'matpis b'davar ha'asur v'lo
mitsar afilu hachi kivan d'ika l'meimar hachi v'ika l'meimar hachi azlinan l'chumra
d'kaima lan stam nedarim l'hachmir. So if you introduce this idea, right,
about like יד שאינו מוכיח, yad she'eino mochiach, here in a way
it would almost be like a כינוי שאינו מוכיח, kinuy she'eino mochiach,
not a יד שאינו מוכיח. yad she'eino mochiach. Because here it's not
like you have an elliptical sentence and you don't know what word
to fill in, it's you don't know how to translate an actual
word that you have present. Right, everybody understand that difference between כינוי
and a יד? yad A יד is you don't know what word
to fill in or there's a blank line here. And if it's
אינו מוכיח, eino mochiach, you don't know what word to fill in.
You could also have like a כינוי שאינו מוכיח. kinuy she'eino mochiach.
You have a word that's ambiguous and could be interpreted in one
of two ways. And the principle is we interpret the more מחמיר.
machmir. So even though you would say לכשר la'kasher or לא דכי
la'dachi or לא טהור la'tahor and it could easily mean like you're
thinking about a piece of חזיר chazir and it wouldn't be a
נדר, we translate it as a דבר הנדור davar hanadur and we
make it, and we assume it's a נדר. Okay, so that's if
you say those things. Similarly, if you say טמא, נותר, ופיגול, tamei,
notar, u'pigul, which are things that are not kosher to eat, but
not kosher to eat because of their status as a קרבן, those
are versions of a קרבן, those are types of, you know, types
of states of a קרבן. Something that is קרבן. So that's also
like making it אסור בדבר הנדור, Asur BeDavar HaNadur, okay, אסור. Asur.
So if you say הרי זה טמא, Harei Zeh Tamei, הרי זה
נותר, Harei Zeh Notar, okay, that's also a לשון נדר Lashon Neder
because the idea of נותר, Notar, טמא Tamei again is ambiguous, but
נותר Notar and פיגול Pigul certainly assume the idea of a קרבן
so it's a דבר הנדור. Davar HaNadur. Okay, כאמרא Ke-Imra if you
say like sheep, כדירים Ke-Dirim or like pens in which sheep are
kept, כעצים Ke-Etzim or like wood, כאישים Ke-Ishim like fire offerings, כמזבח
Ke-Mizbeach like the altar, כהיכל Ke-Heichal like the heichal, כירושלים Ki-Yerushalayim all
of those things are considered are like the world of קרבנות, Korbanot,
again some of them might not be maybe I meant like Mary's
little lamb but could be related to the world of קרבנות Korbanot
and we're going to interpret them להחמיר Le-Hachmir and therefore they're all
לשון of נדר. Now is ירושלים Yerushalayim itself a דבר הנדור Davar
HaNadur or does it mean that if I'm talking about ירושלים Yerushalayim
I mean like the קרבנות Korbanot that are brought in ירושלים? Yerushalayim?
Okay, so we'll see about this but you see how all these
are in the world of קרבנות. Korbanot. The ר״ן Ran does point
out why is it that this last group needs the כ Ke
word, needs the כ, Ke, like? Why didn't you just say הרי
זה עצים, Harei Zeh Etzim, הרי זה אמרא, Harei Zeh Imra, הרי
זה ירושלים? Harei Zeh Yerushalayim? Why do you have to say כירושלים
Ki-Yerushalayim where you could say הרי זה נותר, Harei Zeh Notar, הרי
זה פיגול? Harei Zeh Pigul? So he says the difference is that
the words נותר, Notar, פיגול Pigul and טמא Tamei themselves forefront the
fact that they're forbidden, right? The very identity of something as נותר
Notar forefronts the idea that it's a forbidden object. So therefore you
don't have to say let it be like נותר, Notar, by saying
let it be נותר Notar you mean let it be forbidden to
me like נותר Notar because the whole identity of נותר Notar is
something forbidden. Whereas the identity of something as ירושלים Yerushalayim or as
a קרבן or whatever is not necessarily that its identity of its
being forbidden is not necessarily at the forefront and therefore you have
to do the כ Ke in order to emphasize that that's what
you're sort of you're trying to make it forbidden like this thing.
Okay so נדר באחד מכל משמשי המזבח Neder Be-Echad Mikol Meshameshei Ha-Mizbeach
if you took a vow in any of the things that are
things that are used for the altar אף על פי שלא הזכיר
קרבן Af Al Pi Shelo Hizkir Korban even though you don't say
the word קרבן הרי זה נדר בקרבן. Harei Zeh Nadar Be-Korban. So
it sounds like it's somewhat of a כינוי for קרבן, not like
ירושלים Yerushalayim per se is a דבר הנדור Davar HaNadur right but
that it is referring to it's an it's a way of referring
to a קרבן. Okay. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda Omer האומר ירושלים
לא אמר כלום. Ha-Omer Yerushalayim Lo Amar Klum. If you say ירושלים
Yerushalayim it's meaningless is it because you didn't say כירושלים Ki-Yerushalayim it's
meaningless or ירושלים Yerushalayim without the כ Chaf is meaningless? Anyway we
will see about all of this tomorrow.
And of course I thought that we would be done like a
half hour early but you know the discussion fills the available day.
קרבנות? Korbanot?
קרבנות. Korbanot.